Guide to the Natural Science Manuscripts Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Natural Science manuscripts collection
1817-1918
MS 583
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
6.75
(15 boxes)
An artificial collection of papers of Yale faculty members and other individuals active in the academic fields of astronomy, biology, botany, geology, mathematics, physics, agriculture, chemistry and zoology. The papers of inventors are also included. Individuals and organizations represented in the collection include: Oscar Dana Allen, Jesse Buel, William Whitman Bailey, John Torrey, Attale Riche, Denison Olmsted, Simon Newcomb, James Duncan Hague, Amos Beebe Eaton, Asa Gray, Arthur Williams Wright, Sidney Irving Smith, and the Geological Society of London.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
Arthur Williams Wright Papers (MS 1860). Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library.
Scope and Contents
An artificial collection of papers of Yale faculty members and other individuals active in the academic fields of astronomy, biology, botany, geology, mathematics, physics, agriculture, chemistry and zoology. The papers of inventors are also included. Individuals and organizations represented in the collection include: Oscar Dana Allen, Jesse Buel, William Whitman Bailey, John Torrey, Attale Riche, Denison Olmsted, Simon Newcomb, James Duncan Hague, Amos Beebe Eaton, Asa Gray, Arthur Williams Wright, Sidney Irving Smith, and the Geological Society of London.
Arrangement
Arranged in nineteen sections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Denison Olmsted materials in boxes 13 and 14 were a gift of B. Denison Olmstead, 2011.
Existence and Location of Copies
Journal of Denison Olmsted, 1824-1841 is available on microfilm (1 reel, 35mm.) from Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library, at cost. Order no. HM188.
Science -- Study and teaching; Natural history; Agriculture; Astronomy; Biology; Botany; Chemistry; Geology; Mathematics; Physics; Zoology; Mines and mineral resources; Diaries; Inventors; Scientists; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888; Torrey, John, 1796-1873; Bailey, William Whitman, 1843-1914; Allen, Oscar Dana, 1836-1913; Buel, Jesse, 1778-1839; Riche, Attale, 1851-; Olmsted, Denison, 1791-1859; Newcomb, Simon, 1835-1909; Hague, James D. (James Duncan), 1836-1908; Eaton, Amos Beebe, 1806-1877; Wright, Arthur W. (Arthur Williams), 1836-1915; Smith, Sidney I. (Sidney Irving), 1843-1926; Silliman, Benjamin, 1779-1864; Dana, James Dwight, 1813-1895; Eaton, Daniel Cady, 1834-1895; Adams, Henry, 1838-1918; Agassiz, Louis, 1807-1873; Silliman, Benjamin, 1816-1885; Trumbull, Benjamin, 1735-1820; Geological Society of London; Yale University -- Faculty
- Original accession
  - OSCAR DANA ALLEN (1836-1913)
    Biographical / Historical
    Oscar Dana Allen, metallurgist, chemist, botanist, received his Bachelor of Philosophy degree (Ph.B) from Sheffield Scientific School, Yale College in 1861. He also studied chemistry in Germany. Allen conducted metallurgical work in Pennsylvania for several years. He was appointed professor of metallurgy and assaying and was a member of the Governing Board of Sheffield Scientific School in 1870. In 1873 his title was changed to professor of analytical chemistry and metallurgy. He retired, from Sheffield in 1887 due to poor health, and spent the remainder of his life studying botany.
    Scope and Contents
    This collection consists of letters written to Oscar Dana Allen generally on the subject of botany. The letters are arranged alphabetically by the name of the writer. The letters from Johann Breidler and Schulze are in German.
    - Austin, Coe F., 1878-1880, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Breidler, Johann, 1880-1881, 1883-1884 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - James, Thomas Potts, 1879 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Lewis, John Harbord, 1882 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Rau, Eugene A., 1879-1884 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Schulze, 1879-1880 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - JACOB WHITMAN BAILEY (1811-1857)
    Jacob Whitman Bailey, naturalist, and professor of chemistry, mineralogy and geology at the U.S. Military Academy at West Point, 1834-1857, pioneered in the use of the microscope in scientific work in the United States. In 1856 he was elected president of the American Association for the Advancement of Science.
    His sons were Loring Woart Bailey, chemist and geologist, and William Whitman Bailey, botanist.
    - Correspondence
      - Bailey William Marsh, 1850 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Dana, James Dwight (also, letter of sympathy to William Marsh Bailey on the death of J.W.B.), 1843, 1857 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Mantell, Gideon Algernon, 1849 (Box 1, Folder 8a)
      - Morton, Samuel George, 1846 (Box 1, Folder 8b)
    - Special Files
      - Resolution of tribute and sympathy to family of Jacob Whitman Bailey. Probably delivered by Benjamin Silliman before the American Association for the Advancement of Science., 1857 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - WILLIAM WHITMAN BAILEY (1843-1914)
    William Whitman Bailey, botanist, was the son of the naturalist, Jacob Whitman Bailey (18ll-1857). He graduated (1864) from Brown University where he later became Professor of Botany in 1881.
    CORRESPONDENCE includes letters both to and from Bailey and is arranged alphabetically by the name of the writer of the letter nr by the name of the person to whom the letter was addressed. There is a small group of "Correspondence of Others" containing materials about Bailey.
    SPECIAL FILES is arranged alphabetically by subject or title and includes a few pages of botanical notes form the U.S. Geological Survey, 40th Parallel, on which Bailey was botanist (1867-1868), and a diary extract about a visit to a Yale Psi Upsilon banquet (1902).
    - Correspondence
      - Arms, Charles J., 1897 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Barrows, Ira, 1886 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Bissell, Mrs. J.W., 1892 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Bailey, William Marsh, 1861 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Bailey, Mrs. William Whitman, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Brewer, William Henry, 1880-1902 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Bridgman, H.L., 1886-1902 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Callender, W., 1898 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - Depew, Chauncey M., 1890 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - Catlin, Charles Taylor (1835-1912), 1890-1910 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - Dana, James D., 1865 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - Eaton, Daniel Cady (1834-1895), 1879-1880 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - Finch, F.W. (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - Goddard, R.H. Ives, Jr., 1902 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - Hamlin, Charles E., 1878 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - Hague, Arnold, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      - Hall, A.H., 1889, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      - Hall, Elizabeth N, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
      - Martin, ___________, 1902 (Box 1, Folder 22)
      - Palmer, O.L. (for Clarence King), 1868 (Box 1, Folder 22)
      - Robinson, W.E., 1890 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      - Sprague, Homer B., 1879 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      - Stedman, E.C., 1897 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      - Sumner, W.G., 1890 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      - Townsley, Clarence, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      - Wetmore, George Peabody., 1898 (Box 1, Folder 24)
      - Whitney, w. C., 1885 (Box 1, Folder 24)
      - Vose, J. G., 1898 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      - Watson, Sereno, 1881-1889 (Box 1, Folder 26)
      - Wright, Charles, 1883 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Correspondence of Others
      - Bailey, Margaret Emerson (1886-1949) to Mrs. Jacob Whitman Bailey, (1892] (Box 1, Folder 28)
      - Barnard, Frederick Augustus Porter to James McCosh, 1874 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Special Files
      - Botanical notes, Clarence King Survey, 1867 (Box 1, Folder 30)
      - Diary extract re: Yale Psi Upsilon Banquet, 1902 (Box 1, Folder 31)
      - "Short vacations" -a talk, undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
      - Tribute to the late Charles T. Catlin (read at Psi Upsilon meeting), [1912?] (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Correspondence
      - Wright, Susan Forbes (Silliman), 1861-1863 (Box 8, Folder 284)
      - Wright, Susan Forbes (Silliman), 1864-1875 (Box 8, Folder 285)
  - JESSE BUEL (1778-1839)
    Jesse Buel, a printer and newspaper publisher in New York state, retired in 1821 to a farm near Albany. The elevated and sandy tract of land was unproductive under the prevailing agricultural methods, but by the use of deep tillage, crop rotations, drainage, fertilizers and other new methods he made it one of the best farms in the country. In 1823 he became a member of the state assembly, and somewhat later a judge and regent of the state university. In addition, Bue1 established the journal, "Cultivator," in 1834, and published The Farmers' Instructor (10 volumes), and The Farmers' Companion, or Essays on the Principles and Practice of American Husbandry in 1839.
    Arrangement
    Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by the name of the writer of the letter.
    - Correspondence
      - Armstrong, John (1758-1843), 1822 (Box 1, Folder 34)
      - Thorburn, Grant (1773-1863), 1828 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - CHEMISTRY [Unidentified Author]
    - Lecture notes on chemistry, 1841 (Box 7, Folder 269)
    - Lecture: "Respiration," delivered at [Holmesburgh, Phil. Co., Pa.?], 1840-1841 (Box 7, Folder 270)
    - [Lecture on gases -probably given in Baltimore?], undated (Box 7, Folder 271)
    - "On Meterology", 1841 (Box 7, Folder 272)
    - Lecture Introductory to Course at the University of Maryland [Medical School] re: Apologia for study of chemistry by medical students., 1838 (Box 7, Folder 273)
    - Lecture fragment entitled "Iecture on Carburetted Hydrogen Gas & the Lighting of Cities... Jan. 1837 Before the Athenaeum Society" (Box 7, Folder 274)
    - Miscellaneous notes, undated (Box 7, Folder 275)
    - [Notes on Chemistry], undated (Box 7, Folder 276)
    - Introductory Lecture at Fallsington, [Bucks Co., Pa.], 1841 January 14 (Box 7, Folder 277)
    - [Commencement address - probably given at the Philadelphia School of Pharmacy and Science (see C. of Medicine)], 1840-1841 (Box 7, Folder 278)
    - (Lectures on Chemistry] Silliman gave a series of lectures beginning in Sept 1840 to non-science students and for persons not affiliated with Yale. pp. 1-100, undated (Box 7, Folder 279)
    - [Lectures on Chemistry] pp. 101-200, undated (Box 7, Folder 280)
    - [Lectures on Chemistry] pp. 201-300, undated (Box 7, Folder 281)
    - [Lectures on Chemistry] pp. 301-401, undated (Box 7, Folder 282)
    - [Lectures on Chemistry] pp. 402-447, undated (Box 7, Folder 283)
  - WILLARD NELSON CLUTE (1869-?)
    - Correspondence
      - Kilbourne, Mr. re: ferns, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - AMOS BEEBE EATON (1806-1877)
    Amos Beebe Eaton, soldier and amateur botanist was born in Catskill, NY.son of Amos Eaton (1776-1842), a geologist and agricultural surveyor and natural historian. He graduated from the United States Military Academy in 1826 and pursued a military career, rising to the rank of major general before retirement in 1874.
    While in the Army, Eaton established a notable botanical collection of flowers, mosaes and grasses.
    The letters in this collection are generally about additions to the plant collection being made in 1857. Some letters make reference to his son, the botanist and Yale professor Daniel Cady Eaton (1834-1895).
    The letters are arranged alphabetically by the name of the writer of the letter.
    - Correspondence
      - Cook, George H. (1818-1889), 1857 (Box 1, Folder 37)
      - Cooley, Dennis, 1857 (Box 1, Folder 38)
      - Dana, James D. (1813-1895), 1863 (Box 1, Folder 39)
      - Dewey, Chester (1784-1867), 1857 (Box 1, Folder 40)
      - Eaton, Daniel Cady (1834-1895), 1862 (Box 1, Folder 41)
      - James, Thomas Potts (1803-1882), 1857 (Box 1, Folder 42)
      - Kautz, August V. (1828-1895), 1855 (Box 1, Folder 43)
      - Lesquereux, Leo (1806-1889), 1857 (Box 1, Folder 44)
      - Pitcher, Zina (1797-1872), 1857 (Box 1, Folder 45)
      - Sartwell, Henry Parker (1792-1867), 1857 (Box 1, Folder 46)
      - Silliman, Benjamin (1779-1864), 1857 (Box 1, Folder 47)
      - Westerman, B. & Co., 1859 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - GEOLOGICAL SOCIETY OF LONDON
    18 ALS from members of the Geological Society of London addressed to Sir James Monckton and Sir Archibald Geikie; mainly acceptances for a dinner given in 1907.
    - 18 letters, 1886-1918 (Box 3, Folder 193)
  - ASA GRAY (1810-1888)
    Asa Gray, botanist and pioneer in the field of plant geography, received an M. D. degree from Fairfield (New York) Medical School in 1831. He studied botany independently and with his friend, John Torrey, professor of natural history at Columbia University. Gray published the Elements of Botany in 1836 and the Botanical Textbook in 1842. The following year he was appointed professor of natural history at Harvard University where he established the department of botany. Gray was also one of the founders of the National Academy of Sciences and was a regent of the Smithsonian Institution from 1874 to l888. He wrote many books and articles on botany, including a Manual of the Botany of the Northern United States, published in 1848. Gray is perhaps best known as an early champion of the theories of Charles Darwin.
    This collection consists entirely of letters written to Asa Gray with the exception of a memoir abqut Gray written by William Gilson Farlow. The letters are arranged alphabetieally by the name of the writer of the letter. Most of the letters pertain to the subject of botany.
    - Agassiz, Jean Louis R., undated (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Bailey, Jacob Whitman, 1854 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Baird, Spencer Fullerton, 1846 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Barber, Edwin Atlee, 1883 (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Bentham, George, (1851)? (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - Bigelow, Jacob, n.y. (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - Boott, Francis, 1839 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - B?, 1852 (Box 1, Folder 55a)
    - Bruhin, The Rev. Th[omas]? A., 1878 (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - Burbeck, Anna-L., 1878 (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - Clarke, F. L., 1886 (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - Cleaveland, Parker, 1844 (Box 1, Folder 59)
    - Clinton, George William., 1863 (Box 1, Folder 60)
    - Dana, James Dwight, 1839-40, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 61)
    - Darlington, William, 1855 (Box 1, Folder 62)
    - Denny, A., 0 (Box 1, Folder 62a)
    - Downing, Andrew Jackson, 1858 (Box 1, Folder 63)
    - Durand, Elie Magloire, 0 (Box 1, Folder 64)
    - Eaton, Daniel Cady, 1859-1860, 1866, 1868, 1877 (Box 1, Folder 65)
    - Engelmann, G. to Mrs. Asa Gray, 1855 (Box 1, Folder 66)
    - Fendler, August, 1856, 1868, 1879 (Box 1, Folder 67)
    - Gay, Jacques Etienne, 0 (Box 1, Folder 68)
    - Gerard, 0 (Box 1, Folder 68a)
    - Green, Traill, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 69)
    - Hale, T.J., 1859, 1861 (Box 1, Folder 70)
    - Harvey, William henry, 1851 (Box 1, Folder 71)
    - Henry, Joseph, 1850 (Box 1, Folder 72)
    - Hooker, Sir Joseph Dalton, 0 (Box 1, Folder 73)
    - James, Thomas Potts, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 74)
    - Lapham, Increase Allen, 1844 (Box 1, Folder 75)
    - Lehmann, Johann G. C., 1839 (Box 1, Folder 76)
    - Lesquereux, Leo, 1855 (Box 1, Folder 77)
    - Lindley, John, 1851 (Box 1, Folder 78)
    - McKenzie, 0 (Box 1, Folder 78a)
    - Muir, John, 1873 (Box 1, Folder 79)
    - Montagne, Jean Francois Camille, 1855 (Box 1, Folder 80)
    - Mueller, Ferdinand, freiherr von, 1866 (Box 1, Folder 81)
    - Peabody, Dr. Andrew Preston, 0 (Box 1, Folder 81a)
    - Pitcher, Zina, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 82)
    - Porter, Thomas Conrad, 1856 (Box 1, Folder 83)
    - Scott, R. Robinson, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 84)
    - Short, Charles Wilkins, 1855 (Box 1, Folder 85)
    - Tickner, George, 0 (Box 1, Folder 85a)
    - Torrey, John, 1856 (Box 1, Folder 86)
    - Treat, Selah Burr, 1866 (Box 1, Folder 87)
    - United States Department of the Navy, C. Pickering, 1843 (Box 1, Folder 88)
    - Walker, James, 1855 (Box 1, Folder 89)
    - Ward, Nathaniel Bagshaw, 1851 (Box 1, Folder 90)
    - Whitney, William Dwight, 1866 (Box 1, Folder 91)
    - Williams, Samuel Wells, 1868 (Box 1, Folder 92)
    - Wright, Charles, 1856 (Box 1, Folder 93)
    - Wyman, Jeffries, 1846 (Box 1, Folder 94)
    - "Memoir of Asa Gray, 1810-1888," by W. G. Farlow, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 95)
  - JAMES DUNCAN HAGUE (1836-1908)
    James Duncan Hague, geologist and mining engineer, was trained at Gottingen University and the Royal School of Mines, Frieburg, Saxony. From 1867 to 1870 he was first assistant geologist on the U.S. Geological Survey, 40th Parallel, under Clarence King. The seven notebooks in this co11ection record visits to mines in Arizona, Colorado, Idaho, Montana, Nevada, and other western territories, made during the survey, and give details about geological formations and samples, mining techniques, and ore processing methods. Hague wrote Volume III, The Mining Industry, of the Survey report. (His brother, Arnold Hague, was also a member of the Survey team.) Hague was also a consulting engineer to a California mine, 1871-1878, and in 1878, was appointed U.S. Commissioner to the Paris Exposition.
    CORRESPONDENCE is arranged alphabetically by the name of the writer of the letter. This is followed by Hague's notebooks which are arranged chronologically.
    - Correspondence
      - Capron, Horace, 1872 (Box 2, Folder 97)
      - Janin, L(ouis), 1870 (Box 2, Folder 97)
      - Nichols, Lyman (Jr.), 1870 (Box 2, Folder 97)
    - Notebooks
      - 1867 September 3 -1868 February 25 (Box 2, Folder 98)
      - 1868 February 27 -April 27 (Box 2, Folder 98)
      - 1868 May 23 -June 30 (Box 2, Folder 99)
      - 1868 July 31 August 27 (Box 2, Folder 99)
      - 1868 September 12 -November 12 (Box 2, Folder 100)
      - 1869 Aug supplementary (Box 2, Folder 100)
      - 1869 August -September 25 (Box 2, Folder 101)
      - 1869 October 8 -November 11 (Box 2, Folder 101)
    - AM, "Central and Eastern Nevada," being a draft of chapter VI of Mining Industry by J.D. Hague with geological contributions by Clarence King, Washington, D. C., 1870 (vol. 3 of the report of the U.S. geological survey of the 40th paralell containing sections, by Arnold Hague and S. F. Emmons (Box 4, Folder 194)
  - METEROLOGY
    For additional material on meterology, see the lecture and book manuscripts by an unidentified author in Box 7, folders 269-283. These materials are described under the heading of "Chemistry" in this guide.
  - SIMON NEWCOMB (1835-1909)
    Simon Newcomb, astronomer and mathematician, was born in Wallace, Nova Scotia on March 12, 1835. His father was an itinerant school teacher of New England and Pennsylvania ancestry; his mother was a village girl descended from a family of New England country preachers. Newcomb left home at eighteen to seek an intellectual occupation, travelling on foot first to St. John, New Brunswick and then to Calais, Maine. He worked his passage to Salem, Massachusetts and drifted to Maryland, where he taught country school for seven years. Finally, he introduced himself to Joseph Henry, first secretary of the Smithsonian Institution, who recommended him to J. E. Hilgard, then in charge of the Coast Survey and began a program of self-education. Through the recommendations of Henry and Hilgard, Newcomb was appointed in 1857 a computer in the Nautical Almanac Office, then located at Harvard University. At Cambridge, Newcomb attended lectures at the Lawrence Scientific School of Harvard University, from which he was graduated in 1858. He was commissioned professor of mathematics in the United States Navy in 1861, and in this service he continued at the Naval Observatory and the Nautical Almanac Office until his retirement in 1897.
    This small collection of letters consists primarily of letters from persons scattered throughout the world acknowledging the receipt of articles and books by Newcomb and a few letters of introduction and recommendation. There are, however, interesting letters from Benjamin Gould; Benjamin Peirce, and Herman Schultz and some substantive, scientific letters from William Thomson (later Lord Kelvin), Arthur Anwers and [Winnecke?].
    - Acknowledgements for the receipt of works by Newcomb, 1875-88 (Box 4, Folder 216)
    - Adams, Henry, 1876 (Box 4, Folder 217)
    - Adams, John Couch, 1876 (Box 4, Folder 217)
    - Anwers, Arthur, 1874 (Box 4, Folder 217)
    - Barker, George F., 1879 (Box 4, Folder 218)
    - [Caruthers, G. T.], 1880 (Box 4, Folder 218)
    - Engelmann, R., 1877, 1878 (Box 4, Folder 219)
    - Franklin, F., 1882 (Box 4, Folder 219)
    - Gould, Benjamin A., 1876 (Box 4, Folder 220)
    - Gunther, Sigismond, 1880 (Box 4, Folder 220)
    - "Hu", 1876 (Box 4, Folder 221)
    - Lyman, Chester Smith, 1876 (Box 4, Folder 222)
    - Peirce, Benjamin, 1876 (Box 4, Folder 223)
    - Schultz, Herman, 1876 (Box 4, Folder 224)
    - [S]ouillart, C., 1878 (Box 4, Folder 224)
    - Stru[ver), Otto, 1876 (Box 4, Folder 224)
    - Thomson, William (Lord Kelvin) (Box 4, Folder 225)
    - probably: Friedrich August Theodor Winnecke, (German Astronomer) 1835-1897, 1876 (Box 4, Folder 226)
    - unidentified, 1874-81 (Box 4, Folder 227)
  - DENISON OLMSTED (1791-1859)
    Denison Olmsted was born 18 June 1791 on a farm near East Hartford, Connecticut. He graduated from Yale in 1813 and returned to the college in 1815 as a tutor. During the following year he studied theology with Timothy Dwight and subsequently received an M.A. degree from Yale in 1816. In 1817 Olmsted accepted an appointment as professor of chemistry at the University of North Carolina. In preparation for his teaching duties there, he took a year off to study science with Benjamin Silliman, Sr. Olmsted remained in North Carolina, accepting an appointment in 1822 as state geologist and mineralogist, until 1825 when he returned to Yale as professor of mathematics and natural philosophy. After convincing the college to establish a separate chair in mathematics, he became professor of natural philosophy and astronomy in 1836, a position he held until his death. Olmsted wrote a number of widely-used textbooks on astronomy and natural philosophy. His paper on the cosmic origin of meteors, written after the famous meteor shower of 1833, established his reputation as a scientist. He died in New Haven May 13, 1859.
    Olmsted's papers include approximately forty pieces of correspondence, several journals, family memoirs, lecture notes and some personal material. The journals, written between 1826 and 1859, constitute a valuable source of information on Olmsted's personal life as well as on his scientific career. His extensive and informative lecture notes on natural philosophy, astronomy and meteorology span a period of fourteen years from 1843 to 1857.
    Existence and Location of Copies
    One of Olmsted's Journals ((1824), 1926-1841, from Box 8 Folder 288a) is also available on Film Hm 188.
    General note
    Note--for additional material on early studies of chemistry and meterology see the lecture and book manuscripts by an unidentified author in Box 7, folders 269-283. These materials are described under the heading of "Chemistry" in this guide.
    - Correspondence
      - Appleton D., 1841 (Box 8, Folder 286)
      - Bacon, Delia Salter, 1837 (Box 8, Folder 286)
      - Baird, Spencer Fullerton, 1851 (Box 8, Folder 286)
      - Bowditch, Nathaniel, 1827 (Box 8, Folder 286)
      - Clark, Sheldon, 1853 (Box 8, Folder 286)
      - Cohen, M. M., 1848 (Box 8, Folder 286)
      - Crampton, Rufus C., 1854 (Box 8, Folder 286)
      - DeWitt, Simeon, 1834 (Box 8, Folder 286)
      - Edgar, John (to Lucius Olmsted re: death of DO), 1859 (Box 8, Folder 286)
      - Hall, Frederick, 1825 (Box 8, Folder 286)
      - Halsey, Anthony, 1843 (Box 8, Folder 286)
      - Holcomb, Hiram, 1831 (Box 8, Folder 286)
      - Howe, Hezekiah, 1828 (Box 8, Folder 286)
      - Journal of Commerce, 1838 (Box 8, Folder 286)